<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8' standalone='no'?>
<doxygen xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="compound.xsd" version="1.9.6" xml:lang="en-US">
  <compounddef id="indexpage" kind="page">
    <compoundname>index</compoundname>
    <title>Welcome to the Haiku Book</title>
    <briefdescription>
    </briefdescription>
    <detaileddescription>
<para>Below you will find documentation on the Application Programming Interface (API) of the Haiku operating system. This API describes the internals of the operating system allowing developers to write native C++ applications and device drivers. See the <ulink url="https://api.haiku-os.org">online version</ulink> for the most updated version of this document. If you would like to help contribute contact the <ulink url="https://www.freelists.org/list/haiku-doc">documentation mailing list</ulink>. For guidelines on how to help document the API see the <ref refid="apidoc" kindref="compound">Documenting the API</ref> page. A list of contributors can be found <ref refid="credits" kindref="compound">Credits</ref> page. Documenting the API is an ongoing process so contributions are greatly appreciated.</para>
<para>The Haiku API is based on the BeOS R5 API but changes and additions have been included where appropriate. Important compatibility differences are detailed on the <ref refid="compatibility" kindref="compound">Application Level API Incompatibilities with BeOS</ref> page. New classes and methods and incompatible API changes to the BeOS R5 API are noted in the appropriate sections.</para>
<para>A complete reference to the BeOS R5 API is available on the web in <ulink url="https://haiku-os.org/legacy-docs/bebook/">The Be Book</ulink>. The Be Book is used with permission from <ulink url="https://www.access-company.com/">Access Co.</ulink>, the current owners of Be&apos;s intellectual property.</para>
<sect1 id="index_1book_kits">
<title>Kits and Servers</title>
<para>The API is split into several kits and servers each detailing a different aspect of the operating system.<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__app" kindref="compound">Application Kit</ref> is the starting point for developing applications and includes classes for messaging and for interacting with the rest of the system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__game" kindref="compound">Game Kit</ref> provides classes for producing game sounds and working with full screen apps.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__interface" kindref="compound">Interface Kit</ref> is used to create responsive and attractive graphical user interfaces building on the messaging facilities provided by the Application Kit.<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>A <ref refid="group__interface_1interface_intro" kindref="member">general introduction </ref> to the Interface Kit.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="layout_intro" kindref="compound">Layout API </ref> is a new addition to the Interface Kit in Haiku which provides resources to layout your application flexibly and easily.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__locale" kindref="compound">Locale Kit</ref> includes classes to localize your application to different languages, timezones, number formatting conventions and much more.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__mail" kindref="compound">Mail Kit</ref> includes classes to work with e-mail files, folders, protocols, and filters, as part of Haiku&apos;s unique mail handling system.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__media" kindref="compound">Media Kit</ref> provides a unified and consistent interface for media streams and applications to intercommunicate.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__midi2" kindref="compound">MIDI 2 Kit</ref> describes an interface to generating, processing, and playing music in MIDI format. For reference documentation on the <ref refid="midi1" kindref="compound">The old Midi Kit (libmidi.so)</ref> is also included.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__network" kindref="compound">Network Kit</ref> handles everything network related, from interface IP address settings to HTTP connections.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__storage" kindref="compound">Storage Kit</ref> is a collection of classes that deal with storing and retrieving information from disk.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__support" kindref="compound">Support Kit</ref> contains support classes to use in your application including resources for thread safety, IO, and serialization.</para>
</listitem><listitem><para>The <ref refid="group__translation" kindref="compound">Translation Kit</ref> provides a framework for converting data streams between media formats.</para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
<sect1 id="index_1book_special_topics">
<title>Special Topics</title>
<para><itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><ref refid="libroot" kindref="compound">C, POSIX, GNU and BSD functions</ref></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="drivers" kindref="compound">Drivers</ref></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="keyboard" kindref="compound">Keyboard</ref></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="json" kindref="compound">Json Handling</ref></para>
</listitem><listitem><para><ref refid="group__netservices" kindref="compound">Experimental Network Services Support</ref> </para>
</listitem></itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>
    </detaileddescription>
    <location file="book.dox"/>
  </compounddef>
</doxygen>
